Guide to the John Edward Lane Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John Edward Lane papers
1902-1933
GEN MSS 338
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.25
(3 boxes)
Correspondence and research files. Correspondence includes letters to Lane, with copies of some of his replies, regarding the Beaumont Medical Club, and in response to articles by Lane on William Henry Carmalt, Jean-Francois Coste, Robert Willan, and other subjects. Research files include articles, clippings and notes, in folders entitled "Medical History - General","Medical History - France - École de Médicine, Montpellier", "Medical History - France - St. Louis Hospital, Paris", "Medicine in the American colonies", "Quacks and Quackery"; notes about the subjects of his papers; and three folders of caricatures and cartoons, primarily in French, about medicine and doctors.
Lane, John Edward, 1872-1933
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of John Edward Lane in 1934.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The John Edward Lane Papers consist of material related to Lane's research about the history of medicine, including his biographical articles on several individual figures. The Papers are organized into two series. Series I, Correspondence, contains letters to Lane regarding the Beaumont Medical Club, and in response to several of his published papers, including articles on William Henry Carmalt, Jean-Francois Coste, and Robert Willan. In many cases typescript copies of responses by Lane are on the back of the original letter. Series II, Research Files, consists of clippings, notes, and articles about the subjects of his published papers, the history of medicine, "Quacks and Quackery," and caricatures and cartoons about doctors and medicine.
Medicine -- History; Lane, John Edward, 1872-1933; Beaumont Medical Club; Yale University -- Alumni and alumnae; Yale University -- Faculty
- Correspondence, 1918-1933, n.d.; Series I; 0.8; (2 boxes)
  - BEAUMONT MEDICAL CLUB
    - Beaumont, André A., 1924-27 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Beaumont Medical Club. Printed invitation, 1926 Jun 29 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Crummer, Le Roy, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Harvey, Samuel Clark, 1924-27 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes: Carbon of letter from Harvey to James Alfred Spalding
      Includes: Carbon of letter from Lane to André A. Beaumont
      Includes: Carbon of letter from Harvey to Sophie Beaumont
    - Keogh, Andrew, 1920 Dec 8 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Mendel, Lafayette B., 1926 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Pomeroy, Lawrence A., 1925 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Spalding, James Alfred, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - West, Olin, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Wheeler, James E., 1933 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - WILLIAM HENRY CARMALT
    - "B" General, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bakewell, Charles Montague, 1930 Feb 6 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Bingham, Hiram, 1930 Feb 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "C", General (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Chittenden, Russell Henry, 1930 Jan 28 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Corwin, Robert Nelson, 1930 Jan 28 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Cushing, Harvey, 1930 Jan 24 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Day, Ann, [1930?] Jan 31 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Eliot, Gustavus, 1930 Mar 8 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Elting, Arthur W., 1930 Apr 14 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Farnam, Henry W., 1930 Jan 28 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Fishbein, Morris, 1930 Jan 30 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Ford, Guy Stanton, 1931 Jan 29 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Goodrich, Annie Warburton, 1930 Apr 4 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Graves, Charles B., 1930 Feb 3 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - "H" General, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Hooker, Davenport, 1930 Jan 30 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Howell, Mary E. C., 1930 Feb 18 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Jackson, Edward, 1930 Feb 15, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Jenkins, E. H., 1930 Jan 30 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Jones, Frederick S., 1930 Jan 31 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Keogh, Andrew, 1930 Jan 28 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Lambert[?], Robert, 1930 Mar 18 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - "M" General, 1930, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Mayo, William J[ames?], 1930 Feb 8 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Phelps, William Lyon, 1930 Apr 19 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Pusey, William Allen, 1930 Jan 30 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - "R" General, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Riddell, William Renwick, 1930 Feb 11 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Smith, Herbert E[ugene?], 1930 Feb 10 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Storrs, Lucius, 1930 Jan 31 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Streeter, Edward Clark, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Spalding, James Alfred, 1930 Jan 31 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - "T", General (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - "W" General, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Walsh, Jas. J., 1930 Jan 27 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Welch, Lewis Sheldon, 1930 Oct 3 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Williams, Stanley, 1930 Feb 2 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Winslow, C. E. A. (Charles-Edward Amory), 1930 Jan 28 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Winternitz, Milton Charles, 1930 Feb 6 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Unidentified, 1930 Jan 28 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - ROBERT WILLAN
    - Correspondence of John Edward Lane
      - Barlow, H. M. (Harold Monteagle), 1925-29 (Box 1, Folder 52)
      - Burrage, Walter L., 1926 Aug 7 (Box 1, Folder 53)
      - Fox, R. Fortescue, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 54)
      - Fox, R. Hingston, 1919-20 (Box 1, Folder 55)
      - Greenbank, R., 1929 (Box 1, Folder 56)
      - Haldin-Davis, H., 1931-32 (Box 1, Folder 57)
      - Howell, Mary E. C., 1928-29 (Box 1, Folder 58)
      - Low, R. Cranston, 1926, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 59)
      - Mackee, George Miller, 1926 Aug 28 (Box 1, Folder 60)
      - Martyn, A. J. K., 1928-29 (Box 1, Folder 61)
      - Riddell, William Renwick, 1926 Aug 25 (Box 1, Folder 62)
      - Simmons, George H., 1928 (Box 1, Folder 63)
      - Singer, Charles, 1930 Aug 11 (Box 1, Folder 64)
      - Spaulding, James Alfred, 1919 Sep 15 (Box 1, Folder 65)
      - Sprinz, Oscar, 1929 Nov 19 (Box 1, Folder 66)
      - Streeter, Edward Clark, 1929 Mar 31 (Box 1, Folder 67)
      - Walker, Norman, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 68)
      - Weaver, George H., 1929 Aug 23 (Box 1, Folder 69)
      - Willan, Robert Joseph, 1928-29 (Box 1, Folder 70)
      - Willan, Simon Hunter, 1925 Dec 8 (Box 1, Folder 71)
      - Winslow, C. E. A. (Charles-Edward Amory), 1926 Sep 29 (Box 1, Folder 72)
      - Unidentified, 1926, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Third-Party Correspondence
      - Howell, Mary E. C. to unidentified, 1929 Jan 9 (Box 1, Folder 74)
      - Low, R. Cranston to Dr. [R. Fortescue] Fox, 1925 Jul 23 (Box 1, Folder 75)
      - Wooler, Edward to James Blumer, 1925 Oct 13 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - JEAN-FRANCOIS COSTE
    - "A" General, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Æsculape, 1928 Mar 23 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - American Philosophical Society, 1928 Feb 29 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Army Medical Library (U.S.), 1928 Mar 6 (Box 2, Folder 80)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: Fielding H. Garrison, Box 2, folder 98
    - "B" General, 1928-29, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Beaumont, André A., 1928 Mar 1 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Bowman, Isaiah, 1928 Mar 7 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Bushnell, Sam [Samuel Clarke?], 1928 Feb 28 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - "C" General, 1928-33, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Chandler, J. A. C. (Julian Alvin Carroll), 1927, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - College of William and Mary
      See: Earl Gregg Swem, Box 2, folder 138
      See: J. A. C. Chandler, Box 2, folder 86
    - Connecticut State Library, 1928 Mar 1 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Crile, George Washington, 1928 Mar 21 (Box 2, Folder 88)
    - Crummer, Le Roy, 1928 Mar 6 (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - Cullen, Thomas S., 1928 Feb 28 (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - Cushing, Harvey, 1928 Mar 2 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - Daniels, W., 1928 Feb 28 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - Dawson, Warrington, 1930-31 (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - Eller, Joseph Jordan, 1928 Mar 1 (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - Fairchild, Fred R[ogers?], 1928 [Mar 7?] (Box 2, Folder 95)
    - Farnam, Henry W., 1928 Mar 3 (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - Gabriel, Ralph Henry, 1928 Mar 5 (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - Garrison, Fielding H., 1928 (Box 2, Folder 98)
    - Graves, Charles B., 1928 Mar 5 (Box 2, Folder 99)
    - "H" General, 1928, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 100)
    - Hadley, Arthur Twining, 1928 [Feb 24?] (Box 2, Folder 101)
    - Henderson, Yandell, 1928 Mar 2 (Box 2, Folder 102)
    - Hooker, Davenport, 1928 Mar 1 (Box 2, Folder 103)
    - Hume, Edgar Erskine, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 104)
    - Jenkins, E. H., 1928 Mar 7 (Box 2, Folder 105)
    - Johnson, Allen, 1928 Feb 15 (Box 2, Folder 106)
    - Johnson, Clifton, 1928 Feb 29 (Box 2, Folder 107)
    - Jones, Howard Mumford, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 108)
    - Jusserand, J. J. (Jean Jules), 1928 Apr 2 (Box 2, Folder 109)
    - "K" General, 1928-30 (Box 2, Folder 110)
    - Klebs, Arnold Carl, 1930 Sep 22 (Box 2, Folder 111)
    - Krumbhaar, E. B. Printed thank- you card, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 112)
    - Library of Congress. Acquisitions Dept., 1928 Mar 15 (Box 2, Folder 113)
    - "M" General, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 114)
    - Mackee, George Miller, 1928 Mar 7 (Box 2, Folder 115)
    - Mayes, Frank E., 1933 (Box 2, Folder 116)
    - Meeks, Everett Victor, 1928 Mar 22 (Box 2, Folder 117)
    - Mendell, Clarence W., 1928 Mar 2 (Box 2, Folder 118)
    - Mitchell, Sydney Knox, 1929 May 27 (Box 2, Folder 119)
    - Malloch, Archibald
      See: The New York Academy of Medicine, Box 2, folder 121
    - Morton, Richard L., 1928 (Box 2, Folder 120)
    - The New York Academy of Medicine, 1928 Mar 1 (Box 2, Folder 121)
      Includes: Letters from Archibald Malloch
    - Ormsby, Oliver S. Second page of letter only (Box 2, Folder 122)
    - Osborne, Oliver Thomas, 1928 Feb 29 (Box 2, Folder 123)
    - Packard, Francis R., 1928 Feb 29 (Box 2, Folder 124)
    - Penniman, Josiah Harmar, 1931 Nov 17 (Box 2, Folder 125)
    - Pepper, William, 1928 Mar 1 (Box 2, Folder 126)
    - Pusey, William Allen, 1928 Mar 5 (Box 2, Folder 127)
    - "R" General, 1928, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 128)
    - Rhode Island Historical Society, 1928 Mar 3 (Box 2, Folder 129)
    - Robinson, Mabel [Louise?], 1928 Apr 1 (Box 2, Folder 130)
    - "S" General, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 131)
    - Seronde, Joseph, 1928 Mar 1 (Box 2, Folder 132)
    - Seymour, George Dudley, 1930 Sep 9 (Box 2, Folder 133)
    - Shurtleff, Harold R., 1931 Feb 9 (Box 2, Folder 134)
    - Sleyster, Rock, 1927 Mar 3 (Box 2, Folder 135)
    - Spalding, James Alfred, 1930 Sep 5 (Box 2, Folder 136)
    - Streeter, Edward Clark, 1928 Apr 5 (Box 2, Folder 137)
    - Swem, Earl Gregg, 1927-30 (Box 2, Folder 138)
    - Taylor, Lewis H., 1928 (Box 2, Folder 139)
    - Thayer, W. S., 1928 Mar 2 (Box 2, Folder 140)
    - Tinker, Chauncey Brewster, 1928 Apr 9 (Box 2, Folder 141)
    - University of Pennsylvania Library, 1928 Mar 3 (Box 2, Folder 142)
    - "W" General, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 143)
    - Walsh, Jas. J., 1928, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 144)
    - Williams, Stanley, 1928 Feb 28 (Box 2, Folder 145)
    - Winslow, C. E. A. (Charles-Edward Amory), 1928 Feb 28 (Box 2, Folder 146)
    - Work, Hubert, 1928 Mar 2fi (Box 2, Folder 147)
    - Unidentified, 1928-1931 (Box 2, Folder 148)
  - OTHER CORRESPONDENCE
    - Abbott, Wilbur [Cortez?], 1921 Jan 22 (Box 2, Folder 149)
    - Army Medical Library (U.S.), 1929 Apr 11 (Box 2, Folder 150)
      Includes: letter from Fielding H. Garrison
    - "B" General, 1918-29, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 151)
    - Barlow, H. M. (Harold Monteagle), 1925 Sep 23 (Box 2, Folder 152)
    - Bowman, Isaiah, 1921 Jan 13 (Box 2, Folder 153)
    - "C" General, 1924-27 (Box 2, Folder 154)
    - Cross, Wilbur L., 1921 Jan 12 (Box 2, Folder 155)
    - Cushing, Harvey, 1928 Oct 20 (Box 2, Folder 156)
    - Daniels, Winthrop More, 1927 Mar 11 (Box 2, Folder 157)
    - Dwight, Frederick, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 158)
      Bottom half of letter only
    - Eliot, Gustavus, 1921 Jan 14 (Box 2, Folder 159)
    - Fishbein, Morris, 1924 Jul 22 (Box 2, Folder 160)
    - Fox, R. Hingston, 1921 Jan 27 (Box 2, Folder 161)
    - Fox, R. Fortescue, 1926 Dec 26 (Box 2, Folder 162)
    - Garrison, Fielding H.
      See: Army Medical Library (U.S.), Box 2, folder 150
    - Graves, Charles B., 1921 Jan 13 (Box 2, Folder 163)
    - Hadley, Arthur Twining, 1922 Oct 26 (Box 2, Folder 164)
    - Haynes, John, 1921 Apr 23 (Box 2, Folder 165)
    - Henderson, Yendell, 1921 Apr 22 (Box 2, Folder 166)
    - Hooker, Davenport, 1921-22 (Box 2, Folder 167)
    - Johnson, Allen, [n.y.] Sep 16 (Box 2, Folder 168)
    - Kittredge, [George Lyman?], 1921 Jan 22 (Box 2, Folder 169)
    - Lane, C. Guy, 1925 Jul 10 (Box 2, Folder 170)
    - Malloch, Archibald
      See: New York Academy of Medicine, Box 2, folder 174
    - McLaughlin, Mrs. K., 1924 Jul 29 (Box 2, Folder 171)
    - Montgomery, Douglass W., 1928 Oct 25 (Box 2, Folder 172)
    - N. W. Ayer & Son, 1928 Nov 20 (Box 2, Folder 173)
    - New York Academy of Medicine, 1928, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 174)
    - Osborne, Oliver Thomas, 1921 Jan 13 (Box 2, Folder 175)
    - "P" General, 1924-27 (Box 2, Folder 176)
    - Perry, Bliss, [n.y.] Jan 18 (Box 2, Folder 177)
    - Pusey, William Allen, 1921-28 (Box 2, Folder 178)
    - "R" General, 1924-27 (Box 2, Folder 179)
    - Richard G. Badger Publisher, 1921, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 180)
    - Riddell, William Renwick, 1925 Dec 30 (Box 2, Folder 181)
    - Royal College of Physicians, London, 1926, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 182)
      See also: H. M. Barlow, Box 2, folder 152
    - "S" General, 1920-27, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 183)
    - Spalding, James Alfred, 1928 Oct 23, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 184)
    - Streeter, Edward Clark, 1921 Apr 4 (Box 2, Folder 185)
    - "W" General, 1924-30 (Box 2, Folder 186)
    - Weaver, George H., 1928 Oct 26 (Box 2, Folder 187)
    - Winslow, C. E. A. (Charles-Edward Amory), 1928 Oct 26 (Box 2, Folder 188)
    - Unidentified, 1920-27, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 189)
- Research Files, 1902-33, n.d.; Series II; 0.4; (1 box)
  - Clippings and notes about William Beaumont and the Beaumont Medical Club, 1926, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 190)
    Includes: Silhouette [of William Beaumont?] and Club name, under glass
  - "To Dr. Wm. H. Carmalt on his Ninetieth Birthday", printed poem by David. R. Lyman, 1926 Aug 3 (Box 3, Folder 191)
  - Notes regarding Robert Willan, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 192)
  - List of reprints related to Coste transferred "to the shelves of the Library", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 193)
  - "Medical History - General", 1921-31, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 194-196)
  - "Medicine in the American Colonies", 1902-32, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 197-199)
  - "Medical History - France. École de Médicine [sic], Montpellier", 1925-30, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 200-201)
  - "Medical History - France. St. Louis Hospital, Paris", 1914-33, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 202-203)
    Includes: Unidentified group photograph
  - "Quacks and Quackery", 1916-31, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 204-206)
  - Caricatures and cartoons about medicine, primarily in French, 1913-29, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 207-209)